Guide to the Dept. of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation records, 1932-1986 UA.25.22.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Dept. of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation records
1932-1986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Dept. of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation
UA.25.22.0001
3 Linear Feet
The Dept. of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation (HPER) was created in 1975 by the merger of the Men's and Women's Physical Education Departments. However, formal physical education at Duke University dates back to 1902 when President Kilgo invited Wilbur "Cap" Card to return to Trinity College as Director of a new program in physical education. The collection is divided into two series: General files and the John Friedrich papers series. The General files contain printed material on intramural athletics, personal recreational programs, and physical education. The John Friedrich papers series contains administrative records pertaining to his chairmanship of HPER from 1963-1986, and ranges in date from 1975-1986.
2750 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advanced notice required for use.
Provenance
The Dept. of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1974; 1976; 1986.
Biographical and Historical Note
Physical education began at Duke University when President Kilgo invited Wilbur "Cap" Card to return to Trinity College as Director of a new program in physical education. From 1902-1912, Card worked as both Director of the Gym and coach of various sports such as baseball. After the 1912 season, he stepped aside as coach to devote all of his time to being Director.
Under Card's direction all freshmen, sophomores and juniors were required to attend exercise periods. Card kept meticulous records noting the date of the examination, the student's age, weight, height, the girth, depth and breadth of several body parts (such as knees, thighs, shoulders, etc.), the color of hair and eyes, temperament, and other facts. From these measurements and observations he prescribed exercises that were best suited toward the physical development of each student. These physical examination volumes are located in Card's papers (see catalog).
Between 1926 and 1929, separate Men's and Women's Physical Education Departments grew out of the original department. During the 1930s, the Men's Physical Education Department incorporated a 1 hour classroom instruction (for the freshmen and sophomore students) into the required 3 hours a week of physical exercise for all students.
In the 1940s the Department of Physical Education and Athletics, under the direction of Wallace Wade, went through a period of growth. Due to the WWII war effort the V-12 Program administered by the Navy was established on Duke's campus from 1943-1945. As part of this program students received vigorous physical training 5 days a week so that they would be ready for service if called upon.
The post-WWII period of the 1950s and 1960s brought a new trend in physical education towards supervised group recreation. Elective courses in physical education method and theory were added in 1950 to help meet the increasing demand for teachers qualified to coach and teach physical education. 1960 saw the development of a voluntary intramural sports program that consisted of a dozen sports and involved a large percentage of the student population.
The Dept. of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation (HPER) was created in 1975 by the merger of the Men's and Women's Physical Education Departments. At that time the major, which had been offered to women only, was dropped as was the physical education requirement for all undergraduates. HPER offered theory courses (set of courses dealing with various aspects of physical education or in the administrative use of physical education skills); activity/skills courses (tennis, racquetball, swimming, etc.); intramurals sports program; club sports; DUPAC (adult fitness program); and a faculty fitness program
In 1980, the Chancellor Pye recommended to the Board of Trustees that credit for courses be dropped and that the department become a "non-academic unit." HPER was restructured in July 1981 and made into a division of the Office of Student Affairs. In September of 1981 the Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences (UFCAS) denied Chancellor Pye's recommendation that credit for HPER courses be dropped and reaffirmed HPER's ability to offer credit for activities and theory course with the UFCAS course committee approving the courses.
John A. Friedrich, chairman of Dept. of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation (HPER) from 1963-1986, came to Duke University from Michigan State University where he had directed the physical education instruction program for nine years. Friedrich served on a number of University committees including Curriculum and Policies Committee, Commencement Committee as chairman of staff marshals, The Project Wild Board, The International Club, and The Undergraduate Faculty Council. Materials from some of these committees are located in the John Friedrich papers series below. Friedrich was also on the board of directors of several local associations including the N.C. Lung Association, N.C. Heart Association, and the Durham Cancer Association.
This note was written based on information in an independent study The History of the Development of Physical Education at Duke, by Eddie Falcone and Mike Hamschin located within this collection.
Collection Overview
The General files series in the Dept. of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation (HPER) collection contains materials pertaining to the origins and activities of HPER including material on intramural athletics, personal recreational programs, and physical education. Present in the collection are: flyers, intramural handbooks, clippings, manual for the Men's Physical Education program of 1932, and issues of the Faculty Fitness Newsletter. The John Friedrich papers series contains administrative records pertaining to his chairmanship of HPER from 1963-1986, and ranges in date from 1975-1986. Materials present include correspondence, minutes and agendas from several University committees including Academic Council, Commencement Committee, and Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences (UFCAS), as well as minutes from HPER departmental meetings. Friedrich presided over the HPER restructuring debates of the 1970s and early 1980s and reports, proposals, and clippings regarding retrenchment of the Dept. are present in this series.
Related Material
Committees Reference Collection, 1932-ongoing
University Archives. Duke University.
Educational Facilities Committee records, 1962-1986.
University Archives. Duke University.
Julia R. Grout Papers, 1916 - 1984.
University Archives. Duke University.
Wilbur Wade Card papers, 1876-1943.
University Archives. Duke University.
Women's Department of Health and Physical Education records, 1923 - 1976.
University Archives. Duke University.
Physical education and training -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Physical education facilities; Physical education and training -- Curricula; College students -- Physical training -- United States; Duke University. Dept. of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation; Duke University -- Students; Duke University -- Faculty; Griffith, William; Duke University. Dept. of Health, Physical Education, and Recreation; Friedrich, John
- General files, 1932-1984, bulk 1964-1975, 1 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes material on intramural athletics, personal recreational programs, and physical education. Included are: flyers, intramural handbooks, clippings, manual for the Men's Physical Educatiuon program of 1932, and issues of the Faculty Fitness Newsletter.
  - Brochures, Programs, and Flyers, 1964-1984 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1973-1979 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Fitness Newsletter, 1973-1984 (Box 1)
  - History of the Development of Physical Education at Duke, 1974 (Box 1)
  - HPER Departmental Materials, 1964-1983 (memos, surveys, evaluation of the intramurals program by the MSGA) (Box 1)
  - HPER Staff Manual, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - Intramurals, Handbooks, 1934-1984 [incomplete] (Box 1)
  - Physical Education Manual, 1932; 1967; undated (Box 1)
  - Physical Education Manual for Freshmen Students, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Reports, 1965-1966; 1974-1975 (Box 1)
- John Friedrich papers, 1975-1986, 2 boxes
  The John Friedrich papers series contains administrative records pertaining to his chairmanship of the Health, Physical Education, and Recreation Department from 1963-1986, and ranges in date from 1975-1986. Material present include correspondence, minutes and agendas from several University committees including Academic Council, Commencement Committee, and Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences (UFCAS), as well as minutes from HPER departmental meetings. Friedrich presided over the HPER restructuring debates of the 1970s and early 1980s and reports, proposals, and clippings regarding retrenchment of the Dept. are present in this series.
  - Academic Affairs Committee, Mary Semens sent 11/13/1980 (Box 2)
  - Academic Council, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - Academic Council, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Academic Council, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Academic Council, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Academic Council, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Academic Council, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Academic Council, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Annual Report for Sports Clubs, 1978-1984 (Box 2)
  - Statute of the Associated Students of Duke University Re: Card Pool, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Board of Trustees, Duke University, 1980-1985 [HPER monthly report for BOT] (Box 2)
  - Keith Brodie letters, concerns Dept. merger with DUAA, 1983-1986 (Box 2)
  - Budget Request Items, 1981-1984 (Box 2)
  - Building Fund, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - A, 1978-1986 (Box 2)
    - B, 1978-1985 (Box 2)
    - F, 1975; 1981 (Box 2)
    - G, 1981-1984 (Box 2)
    - H, 1978-1985 (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - J, 1978-1982 (Box 2)
    - K, 1979-1983 (Box 2)
    - L, 1978-1985 (Box 2)
    - M, 1979-1985 (Box 2)
    - N, 1978-1986 (Box 2)
    - O, 1979-1983 (Box 2)
    - P, 1978-1983 [Chancellor Kenneth Pye is a major correspondent in this folder] (Box 2)
    - Q, 1979 (Box 2)
    - R, 1984 (Box 2)
    - S, 1978-1985 (Box 2)
    - T, 1978-1985 (Box 2)
    - U, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - W, 1978-1985 (Box 2)
    - X-Y-Z, 1980-1984 (Box 2)
  - Cox, Bob deceased faculty member of HPER, 1978 (Box 2)
  - De Leon (deceased), 1984 (Box 2)
  - HPER Departmental Meeting, 1976-1986 (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Duke Sports Club Conference, October 22, 1983 (Box 2)
  - HPER East Campus Activity Center The Epoch Center, 1976-1978 (Box 2)
  - Equal Opportunity Material, 1977-1981 (Box 2)
  - Family, Education, Rights, and Privacy Act (Box 2)
  - Family Night/Clinics, 1975-1979 (Box 2)
  - Fencing, [1976-1977], 1982 (Box 2)
  - Graduation, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Graduation, 1983 (contains a staff marshal ribbon) (Box 2)
  - Graduation, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Monthly report to Trustees, 1983-1985 [submitted to Bill Griffith, V.P. of Student Affairs] (Box 2)
  - Bill Griffiths, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Bill Griffith, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Bill Griffith, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Bill Griffith, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Health Fair, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Letters/Memos from staff, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Departmental Memos, 1979-1983 (Box 3)
  - Merger of HPER with DUAA, 1979; 1986 (Box 3)
  - Outdoor Adventure Series, Virginia Cave Trek (Box 3)
  - Personal Effectiveness Grid, 1980-1985 [Memos to HPER staff-subjects include coarse loads, meeting agendas, etc.] (Box 3)
  - Reappointments, 1979-1985 (Box 3)
  - Retrenchment Review, 1979-1981 (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - October 1979 [Retrenchment Review] (Box 3)
  - November 1979 [Retrenchment Review] (Box 3)
  - December 1979 [Retrenchment Review] (Box 3)
  - January 1979 [Retrenchment Review] (Box 3)
  - Future Directions, 1980 [Retrenchment Review] (Box 3)
  - Ann Scott Meeting, February 6, 1980 [Retrenchment Review] (Box 3)
  - Safety-Larry Blake manager, 1983; 1985 (Box 3)
  - President Terry Sanford, 1979-1985 (Box 3)
  - Semester reports-Annual reports, 1978-1985 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Spring Semester C0-ordinator, 1980 [Facilities Management and Maintenance] (Box 3)
  - UFCAS [Undergraduate Faculty council of Arts and Sciences) minutes, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - UFCAS minutes, 1980-1981 (Box 3)